I want you now to imagine
أريدكم أن تتخيلوا
a wearable robot
رجلاً آلياً يمكن إرتداءه
that gives you superhuman abilities,
يمكنه ان يكسبك قدرات بشرية هائلة ..
or another one that takes wheelchair users
أو يمكنه ان يُكسب المُقعدين
up standing and walking again.
قدرة على الوقوف والمشي مرة أخرى
We at Berkeley Bionics
نحن في شركة " بيركلي بيونيكس " لدينا هذا ..
call these robots exoskeletons.
يمكنكم ان تدعوا هذا الاختراع ب " الهيكل الخارجي "
These are nothing else
ان هذا ليس
than something that you put on in the morning,
سوى شيء ترتديه في الصباح
and it will give you extra strength,
وسوف يكسبك قوة هائلة ..
and it will further enhance your speed,
وسوف يجعلك تجري اسرع
and it will help you, for instance, to manage your balance.
وسوف يجعلك تتحكم في توازنك اكثر
It is actually the true integration
انه التكامل الحقيقي
of the man and the machine.
بين الانسان والآلة
But not only that --
ولكن ليس هذا فحسب ..
it will integrate and network you
بل سوف تكسبك تكامل تام
to the universe
مع الكون من حولك
and other devices out there.
وكل الاجهزة الموجودة فيه
This is just not some blue sky thinking.
ان هذا ليس اختراعاً وهمياً .. شديد التفاؤل
To show you now what we are working on
لكي نريكم ما كنا نعمل عليه ..
by starting out talking about
وما هو اساس هذه الفكرة
the American soldier,
انه الجندي الامريكي
that on average does carry about 100 lbs. on their backs,
ان الجندي الامريكي من المطلوب منه حمل 100 رطل
and they are being asked to carry more equipment.
ومعدات اليوم زنتها اكثر
Obviously, this is resulting
ومما هو جلي ان هذا يؤثر
in some major complications --
بتبعات كبيرة على هؤلاء الجنود
back injuries, 30 percent of them --
مما يصيب ظهورهم بالآلام .. ف30%
chronic back injuries.
منهم يعانون من مشاكل في الظهر
So we thought we would look at this challenge
وقررنا نحن ان نأخذ هذا الامر على عاتقنا
and create an exoskeleton
وان نصنع هيكل خارجي
that would help deal with this issue.
يمكنه ان يعالج هذه المشكلة
So let me now introduce to you HULC --
دعوني الآن اقدم لكم " هالك = الرجل الاخضر العملاق "
or the Human Universal
او الانسان العالمي
Load Carrier.
حامل المعدات
Soldier: With the HULC exoskeleton,
الجندي : مع " الهيكل الخارجي " هالك "
I can carry 200 lbs. over varied terrain
يمكنني ان احمل معدات تزن 200 رطل عبر مناطق سيئة التضاريس
for many hours.
ولعدة ساعات
Its flexible design allows for deep squats,
انه تصميم مرن يسمح بدرجات حرية كبيرة
crawls and high-agility movements.
وامكانية مناورة هائلة
It senses what I want to do, where I want to go,
انه يقرأ " يستشعر " ما اقوم به .. والى اين اذهب
and then augments my strength and endurance.
ومن ثم يقوم بتعديل القوة والتحمل
Eythor Bender: We are ready with our industry partner
إيثور بيندير : نحن جاهزون مع شريكنا التجاري
to introduce this device,
لكي نقدم هذا الجهاز
this new exoskeleton this year.
كهيكل انسان خارجي هذا العام
So this is for real.
نعم انه حقيقة ..
Now let's turn our heads
الان دعونا ننتقل الى المجال الاخر ..
towards the wheelchair users,
الى المُقعدين
something that I'm particularly passionate about.
انه شيء انا شغوف به منذ البداية
There are 68 million people
هناك في العالم 68 مليون
estimated to be in wheelchairs worldwide.
مقعد يستخدمون الكراسي في الحركة حول العالم
This is about one percent of the total population.
وهذا يعني ما يقارب 1% من السكان
And that's actually a conservative estimate.
وهذا تقدير أولي
We are talking here about, oftentimes,
نحن نتحدث هنا عن
very young individuals with spinal cord injuries,
الشباب الذين أُصيبوا بخلل في العمود الفقري
that in the prime of their life -- 20s, 30s, 40s --
في باكورة حياتهم .. في 20 .. او 30 .. او 40 من حياتهم ..
hit a wall
حين ارتطموا بواقعة
and the wheelchair's the only option.
ان الكرسي المتحرك هو خيارهم الوحيد لاكمال هذه الحياة ..
But it is also the aging population
ولكن اضافة الى هذا .. يوجد كبار السن
that is multiplying in numbers.
الذين يمثلون اضعاف ذلك الرقم
And the only option, pretty much --
والذي يبدو لهم بصورة جلية
when it's stroke or other complications --
في كثير من الاحيان نتيجة مضاعفات صحية
is the wheelchair.
ان الكرسي المتحرك هو خيارهم الوحيد للاستمرار في التحرك
And that is actually for the last 500 years,
وكان هذا هو الخيار منذ 500 عام .. منذ اختراع الكرسي المتحرك
since its very successful introduction, I must say.
ولكن اليوم .. افخر بأن اقدم لكم
So we thought we would start
ما يمكن ان نسميه
writing a brand new chapter
كتابة عصر جديد
of mobility.
من الحركة البشرية ..
Let me now introduce you to eLEGS
اقدم لكم " الارجل الالكترونية = إي ليغز "
that is worn by Amanda Boxtel
ترتديها " اماندا بوكستل "
that 19 years ago was spinal cord injured,
التي اصيبت اصابة بالغة في عمودها الفقري منذ 19 عاماً
and as a result of that
ونتيجة لهذا لم
she has not been able to walk
تستطع المشي لاحقاً
for 19 years until now.
منذ 19 عاماً حتى يومنا هذا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Amanda Boxtel: Thank you.
أماندا بوكستل : شكراً لكم
EB: Amanda is wearing our eLEGS set.
إيثور بيندير : أماندا ترتدي " الإي ليغز "
It has sensors.
انها تملك مجسات ..
It's completely non-invasive,
انها مجسات غير مخفية ..
sensors in the crutches
تكمن في الركائز
that send signals back to our onboard computer
ترسل معلوماتها الى الكمبيوتر المحمول
that is sitting here at her back.
الذي يتواجد هنا على الظهر
There are battery packs here as well
والذي يعمل على البطارية
that power motors that are sitting at her hips,
ذاتها التي تعذي المحرك والذي يتواجد على فخذها
as well as her knee joints,
كما على ركبها
that move her forward
الذي يدفعها الى الامام
in this kind of smooth and very natural gait.
انها مشية سلسة وطبيعية جداً
AB: I was 24 years old
أماندا بوكستل : عندما كنت في 24 من عمري
and at the top of my game
وانا على قمة الهرم الرياضي في لعبتي
when a freak summersault while downhill skiing
اجتاحني انهيار ثلجي
paralyzed me.
اصبت جراءه بالشلل
In a split second,
خلال جزء من الثانية
I lost all sensation and movement
فقدت كل احساسي بالحركة
below my pelvis.
اسفل جزعي
Not long afterwards,
وماهو الا بضع وقت
a doctor strode into my hospital room,
حتى زارني في غرفة المستشفى الطبيب
and he said, "Amanda,
وقال لي " اماندا ..
you'll never walk again."
لن تتمكني من السير مجدداً
And that was 19 yeas ago.
وكان هذا من 19 عاماً
He robbed
لقد سرق مني كل ذرة
every ounce of hope
امل موجودة ..
from my being.
في حياتي
Adaptive technology
ان التكنولوجيا " المتواكبة "
has since enabled me
مكنتني منذ ذلك الوقت
to learn how to downhill ski again,
من ان استطيع ان اتزلج مرة اخرى
to rock climb and even handcycle.
وان اتسلق .. او ان اسير بعجلات تقاد بالايدي
But nothing has been invented
ولكن لم يتم اختراع اي شيء من قبل
that enables me to walk,
يمكننا من المشي
until now.
حتى هذا اليوم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكراً
EB: As you can see,
إيثور بيندير : كما ترون
we have the technology,
لدينا التكنولوجيا
we have the platforms
ولدينا الامكانية . ولدينا هنا في المؤتمر منصة
to sit down and have discussions with you.
يمكننا الجلوس معكم فيها لكي نتناقش عن الامكانيات التي يمثلها هذا الاختراع
It's in our hands,
انه اليوم واقع بين يدينا
and we have all the potential here
ولدينا الكثير من الامكانيات
to change the lives
لتغيير حياة الكثير ممن حولنا
of future generations --
من اجل الاجيال القادمة
not only for the soldiers,
وليس من اجل الجنود فحسب
or for Amanda here and all the wheelchair users,
بل من اجل اشخاص مثل " اماندا " .. اشخاص مقعدون كثر حول العالم
but for everyone.
بكل بساطة من اجل الجميع
AB: Thanks.
أماندا بوكستل : شكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)